<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>adamdubey.github.io</title>
    <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on adamdubey.github.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://adamdubey.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Homelab Diaries: Making a fancy Cookbook</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/cookbook/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/cookbook/</guid>
      <description>Yo Chef! I love to cook! And like many people, I&#39;ve accumulated far too many cookbooks and recipes, which over time becomes highly inefficient when searching for a particular recipe to cook - especially when time is tight during weeknights. I&#39;ve probably pruned my &amp;ldquo;go to&amp;rdquo; list of recipes down multiple times, but it still just doesn&#39;t serve me as well as I&#39;d hoped.
Initially I began to prototype this project during some free time at work one day using Sphinx, as I already had familiarity working with it for technical documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Build your own Ground Station with PiAware</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/piaware/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/piaware/</guid>
      <description>Surely you can&#39;t be serious&amp;hellip;
Livin’ the dream Over the past few days I had been working on migrating a few services within my &amp;ldquo;Ham Shack&amp;rdquo; to containerized services, which freeded up both space on my desk as well as a few Raspberry Pi&#39;s, which was exactly what I needed to build a new PiAware ADS-B ground station!
If you like data, enjoy watching airplanes fly overhead, and want to contribute to a rapidly growing network of ADS-B ground stations - then this is the project for you (plus it’s really easy and straightforward).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alexa Skills Building: Bad Janet</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/bad-janet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/bad-janet/</guid>
      <description>Project Motivation Lately, I have been working towards gearing up to sit the AWS Certified Alexa Skills Builder certification. Initially, I received a humorous request to bring Bad Janet to life, and saw the potential to create an Alexa Skill that would quote Bad Janet from The Good Place.
From an initial concept, the only &amp;ldquo;tricky&amp;rdquo; part of this project is negotiating the speech synthesis, in which you may have to purposely misspell a word only to have Alexa speak the word correctly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Private NPM Package Development</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/private-npm-package-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/private-npm-package-development/</guid>
      <description>A primer on developing private NPM packages.
Packages galore Outlined are the procedures and guidelines for private NPM package development. This guide is inspired by an old dev team I was on, and frankly this has served me time and time again when working on internal NPM packages at other companies.
One of the fundamental principles a Web Development team should embrace is the software programming ideals behind the old Unix philosophy - You should strive to build short, clear, modular, reusable, composable, and extensible code whenever possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Homelab Diaries: Docker management with Portainer</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/portainer/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/portainer/</guid>
      <description>Taking a look into management solutions for negotiating container sprawl within my homelab.
The problem keeps growing If you are a Docker fan, then this should be a treat! Think about how many times you&#39;ve had to execute docker ps -a just to see a list of all the containers you have running on a given system. Now imagine you are maintaining several servers plus your main development rig&amp;hellip;
Just within my homelab alone, there is a minimum of 30 containerized services, which wasn&#39;t too terrible to manage for awhile (although extremely tedious).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Diaries: Big O Notation</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/big-o-notation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/big-o-notation/</guid>
      <description>A look at one of my old engineering notebooks containing notes about the Big O Notation.
Understanding Big-O Notation The simplest explanation of Big-O notation is that it serves as a metric for algorithm scalability.
If you are currently cringing, or just trying to learn then stick around! You may find the answers you seek&amp;hellip;
All memes aside, let&#39;s break down the opening statement by first establishing an understanding of algorithms first.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploying a React.js app with Github Pages</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/deploying-spa-apps-with-gh-pages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/deploying-spa-apps-with-gh-pages/</guid>
      <description>With a few hours to kill on a lazy Sunday afternoon&amp;hellip;
React.js &amp;amp; Github Pages: Will it blend? This is the first I’ve actually attempted to deploy a React.js project to Github Pages. I’ve certainly deployed way more complicated applications into all sorts of different environments, so this shouldn’t be anything too difficult, right?
(Yea, it’s hella easy - and is a great way to showcase your work!)
So, let’s build a project!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ahoy!</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/ahoy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/posts/ahoy/</guid>
      <description>Welcome! I&#39;m Adam, welcome to my slice of the Internet! 👋
I am a software engineer with a background in Computer Science and Network Engineering. I have an endless passion and curiosity to create and tinker with various hardware and software based projects. My aim is to entertain and share my experiences working with technology - which is the purpose of this website!
As always,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://adamdubey.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://adamdubey.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description>Various projects and demo applications.
 Fibonacci Calculator 🧮 Taking a look at SPA Microservice Architecture from the lens of CI/CD and Docker.
 Javascript30: Project Gallery 🎨 A gallery of all completed projects from the 30 Days of Javascript Challenge presented by Wes Bos.
 React To-Do App 🗒 A humble Todo application written in React.js to showcase simple deployments. You can read more about this project here.
 </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>