<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-29T11:08:25-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">adamdubey.github.io</title><subtitle>Adam's personal blog, mostly containing research on topics of interest as well as project writeups.</subtitle><author><name>Adam Dubey</name></author><entry><title type="html">The Big-O Notation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/big-o-notation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Big-O Notation" /><published>2019-10-12T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-10-12T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/big-o-notation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/big-o-notation/">&lt;p&gt;Reviewing my notes on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;understanding-big-o-notation&quot;&gt;Understanding Big-O Notation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest explanation of Big-O notation is that it serves as a metric for algorithm scalability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s break that down, starting with understanding algorithms. An algorithm is just a series of steps for solving a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, not too bad, let’s take a look at one of the basic questions this notation solves for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How much harder does something get as you increase your input?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire point of Big-O notation is to be able to compare how efficiently one algorithm solves big problems compared to another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you have a giant dataset, a list of names for instance. How would you go about determining the best possible way of sorting or searching this list of names? Imagine if you had a list of 10 names, another list of 100 names, or even a list of 1000 names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what Big-O notation tells you! It tells you how well a particular algorithm will do against various problems, such as searching a list of 1000 names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notation-o1&quot;&gt;Notation: O(1)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as Constant Complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, no matter what you provide as input to the algorithm, it will still run in the same amount of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking our list of names dataset:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 item, 1 second&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10 items, 1 second&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 items, 1 second&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional real world examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Determining if a binary number is even or odd&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Using a constant-size lookup table&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notation-olog-n&quot;&gt;Notation: O(log n)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as Logarithmic Complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s helpful to think of logarithms as exponents in reverse. Basically the calculation time barely increases as you exponentially increase the input numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to our list of names:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 item, 1 second&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10 items, 2 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 items, 3 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real world example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Binary search&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All operations in a Binomial heap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notation-on&quot;&gt;Notation: O(n)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as Linear Complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is probaly the easiest one to grasp as the calculation time increases at the same pace as the input.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 item, 1 second&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10 items, 10 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 items, 100 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unsorted list search&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notation-on2&quot;&gt;Notation: O(n2)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as Quadratic Complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This might be tricky, especially if you don’t like to get mathematical..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember that things raised to the second power means to multiply times itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calculation time increases at the pace of n2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;1 item, 1 second&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;10 items, 100 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;100 items, 10,000 seconds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real world example: Bubble sort&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;notation-on-1&quot;&gt;Notation: O(n!)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Known as Factorial Complexity, and is probably the biggest gotcha when learning Big-O.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;N!&lt;/code&gt; is a bad place in the algorithm world. Like very bad…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It means it’s basically unsolvable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The calculation time increases at the pace of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;n!&lt;/code&gt;. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# if n = 5&lt;/span&gt;
5x4x3x2x1 &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 120
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t so bad at low values of n, as in this example where &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;n = 5&lt;/code&gt;, but it quickly becomes impossible when the values increase. Taking a look at a few other examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;N=1, 1 option&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;N=10, 3,628,800 options&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;N=100, 9.332621544×10157 options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real World Example: Traveling salesman problem&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Given a list of cities and the distances between each pair of cities, what is the shortest possible route that visits each city and returns to the origin city?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this isn’t so much unsolvable, it’s computationally difficult and even more difficult to optimize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this helps shed some light on the topic, while there are many great sources on the Net, these notes serve as a great refresher whenever I have to go under the hood on challenging algorithmic problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the basic takeaways would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Algorithms are lists of steps for solving problems.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some algorithms are good at problems when they’re small, but fail at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Big-O notation is the way to tell how good a given algorithm is at solving large problems.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><author><name>Adam Dubey</name></author><summary type="html">Reviewing my notes on the topic.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Private NPM package development</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/private-npm-package-development/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Private NPM package development" /><published>2019-09-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-09-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/private-npm-package-development</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/private-npm-package-development/">&lt;p&gt;A primer on developing private NPM packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;packages-galore&quot;&gt;Packages galore&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outlined are the procedures and guidelines for private NPM package development. This guide is inspired by an old dev team I was on, and frankly this has served me time and time again when working on internal packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the fundamental principles a Web Development team should embrace is the software programming ideals behind the old Unix philosophy - You should strive to build short, clear, modular, reusable, composable, and extensible code whenever possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the best way to realize such ideals is by taking full advantage of NPM by using NPM for importing 3rd-party open-source packages. Additionally, it is also used to manage and host one’s own internal shared libraries as private NPM packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To keep things simple, imagine you’ve just joined a new team as a Full Stack Engineer - congrats! 🎉 The project tech stack has several private NPM packages specific to your team’s application, perfect for this guide!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The typical first steps when working on a new project or onboarding with a new team would be to clone the project repository and run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm install&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git clone https://github.com/&amp;lt;user-name&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;project&amp;gt;.git
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; &amp;lt;project&amp;gt;/
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;npm &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;install&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll also need to set up the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NPM_TOKEN&lt;/code&gt; environment variable, which holds the NPM access token used for reading packages from, and publishing packages to, your NPM organization. More on this later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;basic-workflow&quot;&gt;Basic Workflow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about workflows… Every organization is different, and there might be some extra steps that aren’t present from this example workflow. However, the fundamentals of this workflow will get you by swimmingly!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a typical development workflow might look like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a branch&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Run Unit tests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Submit a PR&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get a code review from at least two teammates&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Iterate some more&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Merge into Master upon approval&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And so on and so forth… No need to overcomplicate it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-and-publishing&quot;&gt;Building and Publishing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming you’ve followed the usual development workflow, and your changes have been merged into the Master branch, next would be to create a new Task (or Ticket) in your project management software and corresponding Task branch (e.g., &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;T123&lt;/code&gt;). Give the task the same name as well as the version being published (e.g. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;“0.13.0”&lt;/code&gt;). Checkout the branch, and follow the steps below to publish a new version of a private NPM package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-sh highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# If there are tests, ALL must pass!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;npm &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;test&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# This bumps the version and creates a git tag for you&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;npm version &amp;lt;segment&amp;gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# This compiles into the lib/ directory using Babel&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;npm run build

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# This publishes to a NPM repo (using the NPM credentials provided by your organization)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;npm publish

&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;# This pushes up the git tag that was created by `npm version`&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nv&quot;&gt;$ &lt;/span&gt;git push &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;--follow-tags&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon completion of these steps, you’ll need to open a Pull Request just like you would for any other change. The diff should be extremely simple, just check the version in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; as it should change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;determining-versions&quot;&gt;Determining Versions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may not align with your organization’s rulebook, and that’s okay. If you have the choice to establish Versioning guidelines, then this will hold up well for you!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So which version segment to bump? Often it’s best to use Semantic Versioning for shared libraries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means is given a version number &lt;strong&gt;MAJOR.MINOR.PATCH&lt;/strong&gt;, increment the:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MAJOR&lt;/strong&gt; version when you make incompatible API changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MINOR&lt;/strong&gt; version when you add functionality in a backwards-compatible manner&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PATCH&lt;/strong&gt; version when you make backwards-compatible bug fixes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bump the &lt;strong&gt;MAJOR&lt;/strong&gt; version segment whenever you make a backwards-incompatible change to the interface of any utility defined in the library to be published for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing method or function signatures&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing input types&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing return value types&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removing public methods or classes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Changing the name or location of methods, classes, etc..&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bump the &lt;strong&gt;MINOR&lt;/strong&gt; version segment whenever you make a backwards-compatible change to the library that’s more than just a bug fix. Examples would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Adding new methods or classes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Refactoring internal implementation details&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bump the &lt;strong&gt;PATCH&lt;/strong&gt; version segment whenever you fix a bug in a backwards-compatible manner and are not making any other changes to the library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;npm version patch&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updating NPM dependencies that the library uses constitutes at minimum a &lt;strong&gt;MINOR&lt;/strong&gt; version bump. If you were changing a dependency that leads to further interface-level changes or breaking side-effects, then it may constitute a &lt;strong&gt;MAJOR&lt;/strong&gt; version bump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;private-npm-credentials&quot;&gt;Private NPM Credentials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to publish or install private packages to and from your NPM organization, you must provide valid credentials via the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NPM_TOKEN&lt;/code&gt; environment variable. Be sure to export it from your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;~/.bash_profile&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The one shown below is merely an example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;export NPM_TOKEN=28775d0b-ac16-5e5e-045f-70349z13ae75&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most importantly… Do NOT commit the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NPM_TOKEN&lt;/code&gt; value. It must be kept confidential, and if you believe it has become compromised, regenerate a new token immediately!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Adam Dubey</name></author><summary type="html">A primer on developing private NPM packages.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ahoy!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/ahoy!/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ahoy!" /><published>2019-09-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-09-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/ahoy!</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/ahoy!/">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my little slice of the Internet!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am a software/electrical engineer, with an endless curiosity to create and tinker with hardware and software solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this project site is to capture and document various technical projects that I encounter, mainly for future reference as well as educational value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully you will be entertained along the way!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Adam Dubey</name></author><summary type="html">Welcome to my little slice of the Internet!</summary></entry></feed>